In Kenya, 1984 is known
يعرف عام 1984 في كينيا
as the year of the cup,
بعام "الكوب"
or the goro goro.
أو "الجورو جورو"
The goro goro is a cup used to measure
و"الجورو الجورو" هو كوب يستخدم لمعايرة
two kilograms of maize flower on the market,
2 كيلوجرام من حبوب الذرة في السوق
and the maize flower is used to make ugali,
وتستخدم حبوب الذرة لعمل "الأوجالي"
Both the maize and the vegetables are grown
تزرع الذرة والخضروات
on most Kenyan farms,
في معظم حقول كينيا
which means that most families can feed themselves
ما يعني أن معظم العائلات يمكنها
One goro goro can feed three meals
ويكفي "جرو جرو" واحد لعمل ثلاث وجبات
for an average family,
لأسرة متوسطة
and in 1984, the whole harvest
وفي عام 1984، المحصول كله
could fit in one goro goro.
كان يساوي "جرو جرو" واحد
It was and still is one of the worst droughts
انه كان ولا يزال واحد من أسوأ مواسم الجفاف
in living memory.
التي لا تزال عالقة بالذاكرة
Now today, I insure farmers against droughts
حاليًا، أقوم بتأمين المزارعين
like those in the year of the cup,
مثل هؤلاء الذين عاصروا عام "الكوب"
or to be more specific, I insure the rains.
أو لأكون أكثر دقة، أقوم بتأمين الأمطار
I come from a family of missionaries
أنا من عائلة من المبشرين
who built hospitals in Indonesia,
الذين قاموا ببناء مستشفيات في أندونيسيا
and my father built a psychiatric hospital
وقام والدي ببناء مستشفى للطب النفسي
in Tanzania.
في تنزانيا
This is me, age five, in front of that hospital.
هذه انا أمام تلك المستشفى وأنا في الخامسة
I don't think they thought I'd grow up
لا أعتقد أنهم كانوا يظنوا أن أكبر
to sell insurance. (Laughter)
لأبيع وثائق تأمين
So let me tell you how that happened.
دعوني أخبركم كيف حدث هذا
In 2008, I was working
في عام 2008 كنت أعمل
for the Ministry of Agriculture of Rwanda,
في وزارة الزراعة في رواندا
and my boss had just been promoted
وقد حصلت رئيستي توًا على ترقية
to become the minister.
لتصبح وزيرة
She launched an ambitious plan
قامت بإطلاق خطة طموحة
to start a green revolution in her country,
لبدء ثورة خضراء في بلادها
and before we knew it, we were importing
وقبل أن ندركها، قمنا باستيراد
tons of fertilizer and seed
أطنان من السماد والبذور
and telling farmers how to apply that fertilizer
وعلمنا المزارعين كيفية استخدام السماد
and plant.
والزراعة
A couple of weeks later,
بعد أسبوعين
the International Monetary Fund visited us,
قام بزيارتنا صندوق النقد الدولي
and asked my minister,
وقاموا بسؤال وزيرتي،
"Minister, it's great that you want to help farmers
إنه من العظيم أن تساعدي المزارعين
reach food security, but what if it doesn't rain?"
للوصول للأمن الغذائي، لكن ماذا لو لم تمطر؟
My minister answered proudly
أجابت وزيرتي بفخر
and somewhat defiantly,
وبتحد شيء ما
"I am going to pray for rain."
"سوف أصلي لتمطر"
That ended the discussion.
وأنهى ذلك المناقشة
On the way back to the ministry in the car,
في طريق العودة لعربة الوزارة،
she turned around to me and said,
التفتت نحوي وقالت،
"Rose, you've always been interested in finance.
"روز، أنت دومًا مهتمة بالتمويل.
Go find us some insurance."
إذهبي وأبحثي لنا عن بعض التأمين"
It's been six years since,
كان هذا منذ ستة أعوام،
and last year I was fortunate enough
والعام الماضي كنت محظوظة بما يكفي
to be part of a team that insured
لأكون واحدة من الفريق الذي يأمن
over 185,000 farmers in Kenya and Rwanda
أكثر من 185000 فلاح في كينيا ورواندا
against drought.
ضد الجفاف
They owned an average of half an acre
هم يملكون حوالي نصف فدان
and paid on average two Euros in premium.
ويدفعون حوالي اثنين يورو قسط التأمين
It's microinsurance.
إنه تأمين صغير
Now, traditional insurance doesn't work
الأن، التأمين التقليدي لا يعمل
with two to three Euros of premium,
مع اثنان لثلاثة يورو قسط
because traditional insurance relies on farm visits.
لأن التأمين التقليدي يعتمد على
A farmer here in Germany would be visited
يمكن زيارة المزارع هنا في المانيا
for the start of the season, halfway through,
في بداية الموسم، وفي خلال نصف الموسم
and at the end, and again if there was a loss,
وفي نهايته، ومرة أخرى إذا كان هناك خسارة
to estimate the damages.
لتقدير الأضرار
For a small-scale farmer in the middle of Africa,
بالنسبة لصغار المزارعين في وسط أفريقيا
the maths of doing those visits
حساب عمل تلك الزيارات
simply don't add up.
ببساطة لا يضيف ما يُحصل
So instead, we rely on technology and data.
لذلك اعتمدنا على التكنولوجيا والبيانات
This satellite measures
القمر الصناعي يقدر
whether there were clouds or not,
إن كان هناك سحب أم لا
because think about it:
لأنه، فكر في ذلك:
If there are clouds, then you might have some rain,
إن كان يوجد سحب، يمكن أن تمطر
but if there are no clouds,
لكن إن لم يكن سحب، فمستحيل أن تمطر
These images show the onset of the rains
تظهر هذه الصور بداية الأمطار
this season in Kenya.
هذا الموسم في كينيا
You see that around March 6,
حوالي 6 مارس
the clouds move in and then disappear,
السحب تتحرك ثم تختفي
and then around the March 11,
ثم في حدود 11 مارس
the clouds really move in.
السحب تتحرك بالفعل
That, and those clouds,
لذلك، وهذه السحب،
were the onset of the rains this year.
كانت بداية الأمطار هذا العام
This satellite covers the whole of Africa
هذا القمر الصناعي يغطي أفريقيا بالكامل
and that's important, because if you know
وهذا هام، لأنكم إن عرفتم
how many times a place has had a drought
كم عدد المرات التي تعرض بها مكان للجفاف
in the last 30 years,
في الثلاثين عام السابقة،
you can make a pretty good estimate
باستطاعتك عمل توقع جيد جدًا
what the chances are of drought in the future,
لفرص حدوث الجفاف في المستقبل
and that means that you can put a price tag
وهذا يعني أنك تستطيع وضع سعر
on the risk of drought.
على خطر الجفاف
The data alone isn't enough.
البيانات وحدها لا تكفي
We devise agronomic algorithms
نقوم باستنباط اللوغاريتمات الزراعية
which tell us how much rainfall a crop needs and when.
التي تخبرنا كم كمية الأمطار التي يحتاجها المحصول ومتى
For example, for maize at planting,
مثلًا، لزراعة الذرة،
you need to have two days of rain
أنت بحاجة ليومين من المطر
for farmers to plant,
ليزرع الفلاح
and then it needs to rain once every two weeks
ثم تحتاج للمطر مرة كل أسبوعين
for the crop to properly germinate.
لينمو المحصول بشكل صحيح
After that, you need rain every three weeks
بعد ذلك، أنت في حاجة للمطر كل ثلاثة اسابيع
for the crop to form its leaves,
لتنمو أوراق المحصول
whereas at flowering, you need it to rain more frequently,
بينما تحتاج أن يكون المطر أكثر تواترًا في فترة الإزهار
about once every 10 days for the crop to form its cob.
حوالي مرة كل عشرة أيام ليكون المحصول أكواز الذرة
At the end of the season,
في نهاية الموسم،
you actually don't want it to rain,
في الواقع لا تحتاج المطر
because rains then can damage the crop.
لأن المطر بعد ذلك يمكن أن يضر المحصول
Devising such a cover is difficult,
من الصعب وضع غطاء
but it turned out the real challenge
لكن أتضح أن التحدي الحقيقي
was selling insurance.
كان بيع وثائق التأمين
We set ourselves a modest target
وضعنا لأنفسنا هدف متواضع
of 500 farmers insured after our first season.
من 500 مزارع مؤمن عليهم بعد أول مواسمنا
After a couple of months' intense marketing,
بعد شهران من التسويق المكثف،
we had signed up the grand total
حصلنا على توقيع الإجمالي الأكبر
of 185 farmers.
من 185 مزارع
I was disappointed and confounded.
كنت محبطة ومرتبكة
Everybody kept telling me that farmers
داوم كل شخص على إخباري أن الفلاحين
wanted insurance,
يريدون التأمين
but our prime customers simply weren't buying.
لكن عملاءنا المبدئيون ببساطة لم يشتروا
They were waiting to see what would happen,
كانوا ينتظرون ليروا ما سوف يحدث،
didn't trust insurance companies,
لم يثقوا بشركات التأمين،
or thought, "I've managed for so many years.
أو يفكرون، "لقد واجهت المشكلة لسنوات عديدة
Why would I buy insurance now?"
لماذا علي التأمين الأن؟"
Now many of you know microcredit,
يعرف الكثيرون منكم الأن القروض الصغيرة،
the method of providing small loans to poor people
الطريقة التي توفر قروض صغيرة للفقراء
pioneered by Muhammad Yunus,
التي رائدها محمد يونس
who won the Nobel Peace Prize
الذي حصل على جائزة نوبل
for his work with the Grameen Bank.
لهذا العمل مع بنك جرامين
Turns out, selling microcredit
لكن، ليس بيع القروض الصغيرة
isn't the same as selling insurance.
مثل بيع وثائق التأمين
For credit, a farmer needs to earn the trust of a bank,
للقرض، يحتاج المزارع أن يحصل على ثقة البنك
and if it succeeds, the bank will advance him money.
وإن نجح، سوف يدفع له البنك المال
That's an attractive proposition.
هذا اقتراح جيد
For insurance, the farmer needs to trust
للتأمين، يحتاج الفلاح ليثق
the insurance company, and needs
بشركات التأمين، ويحتاج
to advance the insurance company money.
لدفع المال لشركات التأمين
It's a very different value proposition.
إنه اقتراح ذو قيم مختلفة جدًا
And so the uptick of insurance has been slow,
لذلك كان تنماي التأمين بطيء
with so far only 4.4 percent of Africans
مع ما يقرب من 4,4 بالمائة من الأفارقة
taking up insurance in 2012,
ارتفاع للتأمين في 2012،
and half of that number is in one country,
ونصف ذلك العدد في بلد واحد
South Africa.
جنوب أفريقيا
We tried for some years
حاولنا لبعض السنوات
selling insurance directly to farmers,
بيع وثائق التأمين للمزارعين مباشرةً
with very high marketing cost
بتكاليف تسويق مرتفعة جدًا
and very limited success.
ونجاح محدود جدًا
Then we realized that there were many organizations
ثم أدركنا أنه يوجد العديد من المنظمات
working with farmers:
تعمل مع المزارعين:
seed companies, microfinance institutions,
شركات البذور، ومؤسسات التمويل الصغير،
mobile phone companies,
وشركات الهواتف المحمولة
government agencies.
ووكالات حكومية
They were all providing loans to farmers,
كلهم يوفرون قروض للمزارعين،
and often, just before they'd finalize the loan,
وغالبًا، قبل إنهاء إجراءات القرض
the farmer would say,
المزارع يقول:
"But what if it doesn't rain?
"لكن، ماذا لو لم تمطر؟
How do you expect me to repay my loan?"
هل يمكنك أن تتوقع كيف أسدد القرض؟"
Many of these organizations
العديد من هذه المنظمات
were taking on the risk themselves,
تضع أنفسها في المخاطرة
simply hoping that that year,
تأمل ببساطة أنه هذا العام
the worst wouldn't happen.
الأسوأ لن يحدث
Most of the organizations, however,
معظم المنظمات، بالرغم من ذلك،
were limiting their growth in agriculture.
قامت بتحديد نشاطها في الزراعة
They couldn't take on this kind of risk.
هم لا يستطيعون تحدي هذه النوع من المخاطر
These organizations became our customers,
تلك المنظمات أصبحت عملائنا
and when combining credit and insurance,
وحين تجمع بين القرض والتأمين
interesting things can happen.
أشياء شيقة يمكن حدوثها
Let me tell you one more story.
دعوني أخبرك بقصة أخرى
At the start of February 2012 in western Kenya,
في بداية فبراير 2012 في غرب كينيا
the rains started, and they started early,
بدء المطر، وقد بدء مبكرًا
and when rains start early, farmers are encouraged,
وحين بدء المطر مبكرًا، يحث المزارعين
because it usually means that the season is going to be good.
لأنه عادةً يعني أن الموسم سيكون جيدًا
So they took out loans and planted.
لذلك حصلوا على القروض وزرعوا
For the next three weeks,
ولثلاثة أسابيع تالية
there wasn't a single drop of rain,
لم تكن هناك نقطة مطر واحدة
and the crops that had germinated so well
والمحاصيل التي نبتت بشكل جيد
shriveled and died.
ذبلت وماتت
We'd insured the loans of a microfinance institution
كنا قمنا بتأمين القروض من مؤسسة للتمويل الصغير
that had provided those loans
التي منحت هذه القروض
to about 6,000 farmers in that area,
لحوالي 6000 مزارع في تلك المنطقة
and we called them up and said,
قمنا باستدعائهم وقلنا،
"Look, we know about the drought.
"أنظروا، لقد علمنا بالجفاف
We've got you.
لدينا لكم
We'll give you 200,000 Euros at the end of the season."
سوف نعطيكم 200000 يورو في نهاية الموسم"
They said, "Wow, that's great,
قالوا، "واو، هذا عظيم،
but that'll be late.
لكن هذا سيكون متأخرًا
Could you give us the money now?
هل باستطاعتكم إعطائنا المال الأن؟
Then these farmers can still replant
ليستمر هؤلاء المزارعون في الزراعة
and can get a harvest this season."
ومن ثم يمكنهم الحصاد هذا الموسم"
So we convinced our insurance partners,
لذلك أقنعنا شركائنا
and later that April, these farmers replanted.
وبعد ذلك في إبريل، أعاد هؤلاء الفلاحون الزراعة
We took the idea of replanting to a seed company
نقلنا فكرة إعادة الزراعة هذه لشركة بذور
and convinced them to price the cost of insurance
وأقنعناهم لتسعر تكلفة التأمين
into every bag of seed,
على كل جوال بذور،
and in every bag, we packed a card
وفي كل جوال، وضعنا كارت
that had a number on it,
يحتوي على رقم
and when the farmers would open the card,
وحين يقوم المزارع بفتح الكارت
they'd text in that number,
يرسلوا لنا هذا الرقم،
and that number would actually help us
وهذا الرقم يساعدنا بالفعل
to locate the farmer
لتحديد مكان المزارع
and allocate them to a satellite pixel.
وتخصيص بكسل لهم بالقمر الصناعي
A satellite would then measure the rainfall
القمر الصناعي سوف يقدر هطول الأمطار
for the next three weeks,
لثلاثة أسابيع قادمة
and if it didn't rain,
وإن لم تمطر
we'd replace their seed.
سوف نستبدل بذورهم
One of the first —
واحد من أول -
(Applause) — Hold on, I'm not there!
(تصفيق) - مهلًا، أنا لست هناك!
One of the first beneficiaries of this replanting guarantee
واحد من أول المستفيدين من ضمان إعادة الزراعة
was Bosco Mwinyi.
بوسكن مويني
We visited his farm later that August,
قمنا بزيارة حقله بعد ذلك في أغسطس ذلك
and I wish I could show you the smile on his face
وأتمنى لو أمكنكم من مشاهدة الإبتسامة على وجهه
when he showed us his harvest,
حين كان يرينا محصوله
because it warmed my heart
لأن هذا أثلج صدري
and it made me realize why selling insurance
وجعلني أدرك لماذا بيع وثائق التأمين
can be a good thing.
يمكن أن يكون شيء جيد
But you know, he insisted
لكن أتدرون، لقد أصر
that we get his whole harvest in the picture,
على أن يظهر كل محصوله في الصورة
so we had to zoom out a lot.
لذلك اضطررنا نوسع مجال الصورة كثيرًا
Insurance secured his harvest that season,
التأمين أمن محصوله هذا الموسم
and I believe that today,
وأعتقد اليوم
we have all the tools to enable African farmers
أننا لدينا كل الأدوات التي تمكن المزارعين الأفارقة
to take control of their own destiny.
من التحكم في مصيرهم
No more years of the cup.
لا أعوام "كوب" بعد الأن
Instead, I am looking forward to, at least somehow,
بديلًا عنه، أتطلع إلى، على الأقل بطريقة ما،
the year of the insurance,
عام التأمين
or the year of the great harvest.
أو عام الحصاد العظيم
Thank you.
أشكركم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)